George Catlin
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
George Catlin papers
1821-1904, 1946
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Catlin, George
2.3 linear feet
The collection comprises 2.3 feet of papers concerning George Catlin's creation and promotion of his famed "Indian Gallery" of paintings, drawings, and artifacts of North American Indians. Dating from 1821 through 1904, with one item dated 1946, the papers include letters, notebooks and journals, receipt books and loose receipts, printed materials, and other documentation. The bulk of the collection focuses on Catlin's efforts to promote the sale of his gallery to the United States government through tours, including London and Paris, and petitions to various governments to purchase the Gallery. Among the rare printed catalogs and petitions in the collection are exhibition catalogs for the U.S., London, and Paris tours, the earliest dating from 1837. Letters and other documents include letters dating from the 1830s from Henry Clay, Thomas Sully, and William Henry Seward commending Catlin's work, as well as Catlin family correspondence and papers dating from 1821 through the 1870s.
Biographical Note
George Catlin was born in 1796 in Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania. Although trained as a lawyer, Catlin quit his law practice and moved to Philadelphia in 1823 to begin a career as a portrait painter. He gained membership in the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts in 1824, but his career in formal portraiture met with little success. In 1830, Catlin embarked upon his lifetime achievement of documenting the lives, customs, and culture of the declining native American population of the Plains. He spent the next six years traveling, drawing, painting, and writing about the Plains Indians. By 1837, he had amassed enough documentation to hold a major exhibition in New York of Catlin's Indian Gallery of Portraits, Landscapes, Manners and Customs, Costumes, etc. The same exhibition, with an added live show, traveled to London in 1842 and Paris in 1845, where it was met with rave reviews.
Catlin spent the remainder of his life gathering support for the sale of the Indian Gallery to the U.S. Congress. Between 1841 and 1842, at his own expense, Catlin wrote and published his two volume set Letters and Notes on the Manners, Customs, and Condition of the North American Indians. He also wrote numerous petitions and "memorials" to Congress, often including statements from national and international reputable supporters, such as Daniel Webster, General Lewis Cass, the Joint Committee on the Library (of Congress), and the American Ambassador to France. The Smithsonian Institution's first Secretary Joseph Henry strongly supported congressional acquisition of Catlin's work and even provided Catlin with a small studio in the Castle building. All of the appeals to the government for the purchase of the collection were, in the end, unsuccessful and Catlin died almost penniless in 1872.
Scope and Content Note
The collection comprises 2.3 feet of papers concerning George Catlin's creation and promotion of his famed "Indian Gallery" of paintings, drawings, and artifacts of North American Indians. Dating from 1821 through 1904, with one item dated 1946, the papers include letters, notebooks and journals, receipt books and loose receipts, printed materials, and other documentation. The bulk of the collection focuses on Catlin's efforts to promote the sale of his gallery to the United States government through tours, including London and Paris, and petitions to various governments to purchase the Gallery. Among the rare printed catalogs and petitions in the collection are exhibition catalogs for the U.S., London, and Paris tours, the earliest dating from 1837. Letters and other documents include letters dating from the 1830s from Henry Clay, Thomas Sully, and William Henry Seward commending Catlin's work, as well as Catlin family correspondence and papers dating from 1821 through the 1870s.
Of particular interest in the collection are letters to and from Catlin, including two written by Catlin during his early travels to the west in the 1830s. Other letters include ones from Henry Clay, John Adams Dix, Ralph Randolph Gurley, James Hall, William Henry Seward, Thomas Sully (illustrated), and Baron Friederich von Humbolt, among others. Most wish Catlin well and offer support in his endeavors to sell his collection.
Also found within the collection are several notebooks and notes describing Native American ceremonies, name translations, customs, and other information pertinent to Catlin's catalog, two volume book, and exhibitions of the "Indian Gallery." There are also numerous loose receipts and account and receipt books documenting the 1840s London and Paris venues of the "Indian Gallery" exhibition. The collection also houses printed catalogs for the exhibitions, including a rare 1837 catalog for the first show in New York.
Additional materials include certificates of authenticity testifying to the authenticity of Catlin's paintings from life of Native American sitters, announcements relating to exhibition openings, printed memorials and petitions to Congress, printed letters of support, envelopes and name cards, and handwritten tickets to Catlin lectures. Also found are a handwritten journal of Theodore B. Catlin, photogravures of Catlin, obituaries for Catlin, and printed reviews of the exhibitions.
Arrangement
The George Catlin papers are arranged into five series based primarily on document type. Within each series, materials are arranged in chronological order.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1821-1885 (Boxes 1, 6; Reel 5824; 12 folders)
Series 2: Writings, 1825-circa 1872 (Boxes 1, 6; Reel 5824; 9 folders)
Series 3: Financial Records, 1826-1848 (Boxes 2, 6; Reels 5824-5825; 13 folders, 3 bound volumes)
Series 4: Catalogs, 1837-1871 (Boxes 3-5; Reel 5825; 1 linear foot)
Series 5: Ephemera and Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1832-1904, 1946 (Boxes 5-6, OV 7; Reel 5825; 14 folders)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects-Topical:
Art and race; Indians of North America -- Portraits; Portrait painters; Illustrators; Miniature painters; Painters; Ethnological illustrators; Ethnological painters
Types of Materials:
Photogravures
Names:
Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872; Sully, Thomas, 1783-1872; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852
Provenance
The papers of George Catlin were transferred to the Archives of American Art by the Library of the Smithsonian's National Collection of Fine Arts, now the Smithsonian's American Art Museum. Accession records indicate that the papers were once maintained by the Smithsonian's Bureau of Ethnology and were probably part of the orginal 1879 acquisition of Catlin's Indian Gallery by the Smithsonian. Businessman Joseph Harrison rescued the "Indian Gallery" from Catlin's creditors in the 1850s and stored the collection in a Philadelphia warehouse, where it suffered damage from at least two fires before Harrison's widow donated the collection to the Smithsonian.
Related Material
The Archives holds several related collections of differing provenances related to George Catlin, including a small collection of manuscripts and drawings microfilmed on reel 1191 related to Catlin's work in marine art and documentation. A microfilmed loan of circa 500 items is also available on reel 3277 of letters between Catlin and Sir Thomas Phillipps, 1840-1860, writings by Catlin and material on Catlin's Indian Gallery, including clippings, catalogs, handbills, invitations, drawings and portrait sketches of native Americans, and printed material; a watercolor sketchbook; a list of paintings; and miscellany. Also found within the Archives is one undated letter microfilmed on reel D8 from Catlin, and a collection of art historian William Truettner's research papers on George Catlin.
Restrictions on Access
A digitized version of the microfilm of this collection is available online via the Archives of American Art website.
Alternative Forms Available
The microfilm for this collection has been digitized and is available online via the Archives of American Art website.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence,1821-1885, Series 1:; (Boxes 1, 6; Reel 5824; 12 folders)
  Letters to and from Catlin, including two written while traveling in the west in the 1830s. Also found are family letters and several letters of support from Henry Clay, John Adams Dix, Ralph Randolph Gurley, James Hall, William Henry Seward, Thomas Sully (illustrated), and Baron Friederich von Humbolt, among others. Most wish Catlin well and offer support in his endeavors to promote and sell his collection. Folder headings include all oversize material.
  - Correspondence, 1821, 1824 (Reel 5824, Frame 17-29)
  - Correspondence, 1834-1839 (Reel 5824, Frame 30-50)
  - Correspondence, 1839 (Reel 5824, Frame 51-73)
  - Correspondence, 1840-1842 (Reel 5824, Frame 74-96)
  - Correspondence, circa 1840s (Reel 5824, Frame 97-129)
  - Correspondence, 1843-1844 (Reel 5824, Frame 130-146)
  - Correspondence, 1845-1849 (Reel 5824, Frame 147-160)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1855 (Reel 5824, Frame 161-176)
  - Correspondence, 1861 (Reel 5824, Frame 177-179)
  - Correspondence, 1870, 1874 (Reel 5824, Frame 180-187)
  - Correspondence, 1885 (Reel 5824, Frame 188-208)
  - Transcripts of Correspondence Concerning Catlin, undated (Reel unfilmed)
- Writings,1825-circa 1872, Series 2:; (Boxes 1, 6; Reel 5824; 9 folders)
  This series includes several handwritten notebooks by Catlin, as well as printed memorials and petitions written by Catlin. Also found is a handwritten French translation of Catlin's 1845 exhibition catalog and a partial handwritten manuscript "Travels in Europe." The subscription notebook was originally created circa 1825 to record subscription sales for a printed version of a portrait of the Hon. Tapping Reeve, a Connecticut judge painted by Catlin. The printing was never actually undertaken, however, and the book was later used in 1841 as a memo book during Catlin's stay in London. Of particular interest are the Notebooks numbered 6 and 7. Both contain notes about Catlin's paintings and exhibitions, as well as cultural information about the Indian tribes, such as name translations. One notebook describes a Mandan battle in gruesome detail.
  - George Catlin's Subscription and Expense Notebook, 1825, 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 209-227)
  - George Catlin's Notebook #6, circa 1830s (Reel 5824, Frame 228-252)
  - George Catlin's Notebook #7, circa 1830s (Reel 5824, Frame 253-273)
  - George Catlin's Notebook with Notations about Paintings, circa 1840s (Reel 5824, Frame 274-292)
  - Handwritten Catalog Raisonne, French Translation, author unknown (1 of 4), circa 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 293-317)
  - Handwritten Catalog Raisonne, French Translation, author unknown (2 of 4), circa 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 318-342)
  - Handwritten Catalog Raisonne, French Translation, author unknown (3 of 4), circa 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 343-367)
  - Handwritten Catalog Raisonne, French Translation, author unknown (4 of 4), circa 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 368-387)
  - Printed, "Memorial" by George Catlin to Congress, 1868 (Reel 5824, Frame 388-395)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Reminiscences by George Catlin, 1869 (Reel 5824, Frame 396-402)
  - Printed, Petition to Congress and Leaflet, circa 1872 (Reel 5824, Frame 403-408)
  - Printed, "Synopsis of the Travels of George Catlin in Gathering His Sketches for His Indian Collection", circa 1872 (Reel 5824, Frame 409-417)
  - Handwritten Partial Book Manuscript, "Travels In Europe" (1 of 3), undated (Reel 5824, Frame 418-442)
  - Handwritten Partial Book Manuscript, "Travels In Europe" (2 of 3), undated (Reel 5824, Frame 443-467)
  - Handwritten Partial Book Manuscript, "Travels In Europe" (3 of 3), undated (Reel 5824, Frame 468-484)
- Financial Records, 1826-1848, Series 3:; (Boxes 2, 6; Reels 5824-5825; 13 folders, 3 bound volumes)
  This series includes bound and loose accounts, receipts, and invoices, primarily those of George Catlin for his travels in Europe associated with the exhibitions, as well as receipts for advertising and space rental for the exhibitions. One account book is marked on the cover "Clara B. Catlin Account Book", which actually documents book sales. Also found is one very small bound green daybook decorated with metal tabs and a cover label engraved, "Souvenir." It is unclear who is the author of the entries. Inside is a handwritten inscription dated 1827 on the title page, along with an illegible name. The book includes notes, addresses, account entries, and "doodles." Folder headings include all oversize material.
  - Bound, Miscellaneous Account and Receipt Book (1 of 4), 1826-1838 (Reel 5824, Frame 485-509)
  - Bound, Miscellaneous Account and Receipt Book (2 of 4), 1826-1838 (Reel 5824, Frame 510-534)
  - Bound, Miscellaneous Account and Receipt Book (3 of 4), 1826-1838 (Reel 5824, Frame 535-559)
  - Bound, Miscellaneous Account and Receipt Book (4 of 4), 1826-1838 (Reel 5824, Frame 560-585)
  - Bound Daybook, "Souvenir", Unknown Author, 1827-1830 (Reel 5824, Frame 586-606)
  - Bound Account Book, Book Sales,undated (Reel 5824, Frame 607-613)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (1 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 614-643)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (2 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 644-673)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (3 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 674-703)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (4 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 704-733)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (5 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 734-763)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (6 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 764-793)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (7 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 794-823)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (8 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 824-853)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (9 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 854-883)
  - Bound "Memorandum" and Receipt Notebook (10 of 10), 1841 (Reel 5824, Frame 884-902)
  - Bound Paris Hall Receipts (1 of 4), 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 903-932)
  - Bound Paris Hall Receipts (2 of 4), 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 933-962)
  - Bound Paris Hall Receipts (3 of 4), 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 963-992)
  - Bound Paris Hall Receipts (4 of 4), 1845 (Reel 5824, Frame 993-1106)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts, 1833-1839 (Reel 5824, Frame 1107-1127)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (1 of 4), 1840, (2 folders) (Reel 5824, Frame 1128-1143)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (2 of 4), 1840, (2 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 12-41)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (3 of 4), 1840, (2 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 42-71)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (4 of 4), 1840, (2 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 72-97)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts, 1841 (Reel 5825, Frame 98-108)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts, 1842 (Reel 5825, Frame 109-110)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (1 of 2), 1843 (Reel 5825, Frame 111-140)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (2 of 2), 1843 (Reel 5825, Frame 141-163)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts, 1844 (Reel 5825, Frame 164-165)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (1 of 2), 1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 166-190)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts (2 of 2), 1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 191-205)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts, 1848 (Reel 5825, Frame 206-207)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Invoices and Receipts, undated (Reel 5825, Frame 208-223)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Material,1841-1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 224-229)
- Catalogs, 1837-1871, Series 4:; (Boxes 3-5; Reel 5825; 1.0 linear foot)
  Printed catalogs and duplicates for the Indian Gallery exhibitions in the United States and Europe. The series is arranged chronologically by publication date. Duplicate copies are grouped together in folders. Folder headings include all oversize material.
  - Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Gallery of Portraits, Landscapes, Manners and Customs, Costumes, Etc. (New York, first edition),1837, (2 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 230-253)
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Gallery; Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representations of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians (London edition, C. & J. Adlard Printers),circa 1840 (Reel 5825, Frame 254-279)
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Gallery; Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representations of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians (London edition, C. & J. Adlard Printers) (1 of 2),circa 1843, (4 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 280-299)
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Gallery; Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representations of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians (London edition, C & J Adlard Printers) (2 of 2),circa 1843, (4 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 300-319)
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Gallery, Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representations of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians, (New York, first edition) (1 of 2),1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 320-339)
    Includes insert, "Opinions of the English and United States Press on Catlin's North American Indian Museum."
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Gallery, Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representations of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians, (New York, first edition) (2 of 2),1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 340-359)
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Gallery, Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representation of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians (London edition, C. & J. Adlard), 1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 360-385)
    Includes insert, Catalogue Raisonné de la Galerie Indienne de Mr. Catlin (Paris edition, Imprimerie de Wittersheim)
  - Catalogue Raisonné de La Galerie Indienne de Mr. Catlin (Paris edition, Imprimerie de Wittersheim) (1 of 2), 1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 386-410)
  - Catalogue Raisonné de La Galerie Indienne de Mr. Catlin (Paris edition, Imprimerie de Wittersheim) (2 of 2), 1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 411-437)
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Collection; Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representatives of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians (notated London edition, self-published) (1 of 2),1848, (2 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 438-467)
  - A Descriptive Catalogue of Catlin's Indian Collection; Containing Portraits, Landscapes, Costumes, Etc., and Representatives of the Manners and Customs of the North American Indians (notated London edition, self-published) (2 of 2),1848, (2 folders) (Reel 5825, Frame 468-486)
  - Catalogue Descriptive and Instructive of Catlin's Indian Cartoons: Portraits, Types and Customs and LaSalle's Discoveries (New York edition, Baker and Godwin, printers) (1 of 2), 1871 (Reel 5825, Frame 487-510)
  - Catalogue Descriptive and Instructive of Catlin's Indian Cartoons: Portraits, Types and Customs and LaSalle's Discoveries (New York edition, Baker and Godwin, printers) (2 of 2), 1871 (Reel 5825, Frame 511-537)
- Ephemera and Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1832-1904, 1946, Series 5:; (Boxes 5, 6, OV 7; Reel 5825; 14 folders)
  This series consists of exhibition announcements, certifications of authenticity for Catlin's portraits and other paintings, miscellaneous broadsides, announcements, clippings, petitions in support of the proposed purchase of the Indian Gallery by Congress, obituaries for George Catlin, reviews of the exhibitions, photogravures of Catlin, and a handwritten journal belonging to Catlin's son, Theodore, and other miscellaneous handwritten documents and printed matter. Additional items of interest include a sheet music cover print used to advertise a music and dance performance by North American Indians who accompanied Catlin as part of his Indian Gallery exhibition in Paris and a handpainted mineral chart of previously unknown clay specimens gathered by Catlin during his travels among Indians in Minnesota, later named "Catlinite" in his honor. Folder headings include all oversize material.
  - Certificates of Authenticity, 1832-1836, 1872, undated (Reel 5825, Frame 538-544)
  - Reviews, circa 1837-1889 (Reel 5825, Frame 545-564)
  - Copyright Registration for Letters and Notes on the Manners, Customs, and Condition of the North American Indians,1841 (Reel 5825, Frame 565-568)
  - London Subscription Form for Purchasing Letters and Notes on the Manners, Customs, and Condition of the North American Indians, circa 1840-1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 569-570)
  - Rules and Regulations for the Government of the Athenaeum (London) (1 of 3),1840 (Reel 5825, Frame 571-595)
  - Rules and Regulations for the Government of the Athenaeum (London) (2 of 3),1840 (Reel 5825, Frame 596-615)
  - Rules and Regulations for the Government of the Athenaeum (London) (3 of 3),1840 (Reel 5825, Frame 616-635)
  - Handwritten Tickets to Catlin Lecture by George Catlin, undated (Reel 5825, Frame 636-638)
  - Petitions to U. S. Congress to Authorize Purchase of Catlin's Indian Collection, circa 1840s-1875 (Reel 5825, Frame 639-660)
  - Miscellaneous Announcements, Broadside, and Clippings, 1840-1850, 1904, 1946 (Reel 5825, Frame 661-673)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Matter (1 of 2), circa 1845-1889 (Reel 5825, Frame 674-693)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Matter (2 of 2), circa 1845-1889 (Reel 5825, Frame 694-714)
  - Envelopes, Name Cards, and Miscellaneous Collected Items, 1849-1861, undated (Reel 5825, Frame 715-723)
  - Photocopies of Title Pages for Letters by George Catlin Describing the Manners, Customs, and Conditions of the North American Indians (New York Commercial Advertisers), undated (Reel 5825, Frame 724-726)
  - Obituaries for George Catlin, 1872 (Reel 5825, Frame 727-732)
  - Theodore B. Catlin's Miscellaneous Journal (London), 1845 (Reel 5825, Frame 733-753)
  - Photographs and Photogravure of George Catlin, 1868, undated (Reel 5825, Frame 754-760)
  - Handpainted Mineral Chart, circa 1830s (Reel unfilmed)